The world's always been
more beautiful in your mind, Father.
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
He had been
around the world 65 times…
…enlisted in a crew of expatriate sailors.
He had been shipwrecked
and spent two weeks adrift
in the Sea of Japan.
Our ship sank in a storm.
Another sailor and I
were adrift for several days,
holding on to a piece of wood.
Huh! I was the only one who survived.
Mm-hm.
But there were two of you.
What happened to the other one?
He succumbed to heatstroke.
Hmm. But he saved my life.
His flesh… was salty.
It was delicious.
And sweet too.
Úrsula wept at the table
as if she were reading the letters
that never arrived…
…in which José Arcadio told her
about his triumphs and misfortunes.
You've always had a house here, son.
And we've had so much food to spare here.
When you disappeared,
I went running after you.
I walked down every single path
until there were no more left to follow.
Until I was out of ideas
of where to find you.
So, who's this guy?
Hello. I am Pietro Crespi.
I'm Rebeca's fiancé.
And you are?
Your sister, Rebeca.
Little brother.
José Arcadio…
Where were you?
Around.
I moved to
the second floor after I got married.
And Arcadio used to stay in here
until he left the house.
Arcadio?
Your son.
I'll always remember
when you'd come back at dawn
after sneaking out of our room,
and then you'd tell me
all about your adventures.
Then one time, I decided to ask you…
about what all of that felt like.
And then you said,
"It's like the whole world is shaking."
You were right. Do you remember?
It's enough for you to remember.
So, you got married, huh?
I got married.
Now I'm a widower.
End of the story.
Hey, and Catarino's?
That still exist?
Hey, pour me another one!
José Arcadio ordered music
and aguardiente for everyone on him.
Hey!
His monumental body
instilled a frenzy of curiosity
among the women.
Ah!
He proposed
raffling himself off to the women
for ten pesos a ticket.
An exorbitant price…
All right…
…as the most popular woman
earned eight pesos a night.
Teresa!
But they all accepted.
Hey!
Ah!
Come on!
Make way!
Ah!
Whoo!
I'm sure you're aware
that it is almost time for
our first-ever elections here in Macondo.
Starting today up until election day,
there will be a curfew in place
from 8:00 in the evening
till 6:00 in the morning.
From now on, the sale and consumption
of any alcoholic beverages
will be prohibited,
as well as gatherings
of more than three people
who are not from the same family.
Arcadio resorted
to the only person
that had foreseen the abuse
of the Conservative regime.
-Who is it?
-Arcadio. The school director.
Hey.
The things you said would happen
are happening.
We gotta act now.
Doctor Alirio Noguera
had arrived in Macondo a short while ago,
carrying a medicinal kit
of tasteless globules
and a diploma
from the University of Leipzig
that he had forged himself.
Behind the innocent facade
of an unprestigious doctor,
hid a terrorist.
What's this one doing here?
-He's the mayor's little pawn.
-I'm not anyone's pawn.
All right, all right.
Settle down, settle down.
He's one of us.
Those little bottles
full of white globules
were the symbol of an uprising.
Welcome to the revolution.
Thank you.
Marry again, my boy.
I have six daughters.
There's rumors
in the capital of the province
that say the liberals
are willing to go to war.
Well, what are their reasons?
They don't need any reasons, son.
Liberals are ill-tempered individuals.
Supporting the murder of priests,
civil marriage, and divorce.
And they argue illegitimate children
should have equal rights
to legitimate ones.
You're aware of what I think
about illegitimate children.
That's different.
Aureliano José has
his father's Buendía name.
And the name Moscote like his mother.
It's very different.
The truth is, sir, none of those matters
appeal to me even in the least.
Maybe they should, though.
Now more than ever,
it's better to stay on the winning side.
Hmm.
Because we are
against utilitarianism.
Dr. Noguera made contact
with the young people in town
who were not well-versed in politics.
…the secular state.
And embarked on
a stealthy campaign of instigation.
Nobody here ever
talked about politics or parties.
Yeah, but your parents and grandparents
founded Macondo
based on the same principles
as the Liberal Party.
I come from Riohacha.
I'm looking for Doctor Noguera.
I am Doctor Noguera.
General Medina has sent
the shipment you requested.
Yah!
Come on, let's go.
It was the proximity
of the elections
that sparked
the flame of subversion in Doctor Noguera.
Almost every child
of the founders became involved.
And even though none of them knew exactly
what their plan consisted of,
most were enthusiastic
about the idea of eliminating
the Conservative establishment.
FREE AND SOVEREIGN MACONDO
VOTE RED VOTE LIBERAL
I'm voting with you.
My friends, we musn't let
the Conservatives rob the elections.
And Arcadio was growing
more and more excited
over the prospect
of an imminent revolution.
Here. Pass these out.
-Free and Sovereign. Right here, see?
-Right here?
I appreciate it.
There was talk
of executing Father Nicanor,
of turning the church into a school,
and instituting free love.
VOTE BLUE FOR PRESIDENT
VOTE FOR THE CONSERVATIVE PARTY
FREE AND SOVEREIGN MACONDO
VOTE RED VOTE LIBERAL
That morning when she saw him…
…Rebeca thought of Pietro Crespi
as a foppish weakling
when compared to that superior being
whose volcanic breathing could be heard
throughout the house.
You have no right to do this!
Understand? Understand what?
There's nothing I need to understand.
You can't leave me without those knives!
These are orders from the mayor,
all right lady?
Oh, yeah? Is that so?
Hmm. Well, the mayor will listen
to what I have to say!
-And now how am I supposed to work? Huh?
-Hmm.
Tell me, young man. Huh?
Hey, stop that!
What are you doing in there?
What do you think you're doing?
There's nothing to look at in there!
How dare you rummage through
our things like this?
Young man! Don't you test my patience!
-Orders are orders!
-Don't test my patience!
I am warning you!
Young man, give me back my knives!
I'm warning you!
You can have them back
once the elections are over.
Young man!
What am I supposed to
finish cooking with now?
Get back here!
What are you doing?
-Give me my knives back!
-Do not take my knives!
-No!
-At least let me cut the meat.
What's going on?
How do they expect to eat?
It's your knife.
Just go, "Get out of here!"
This town is a mess.
-We just need to check.
-Ridiculous.
Matilde…
how can they treat us like criminals?
What right do you have?
We've done nothing to deserve this!
We can't even cook.
FREE AND SOVEREIGN MACONDO
VOTE RED VOTE LIBERAL
Why are you
seizing our property?
Who do they think they are,
coming in here
and taking whatever they want?
What's going on?
Nobody's bothered to tell us anything.
-What do those posters say?
-We have to do something.
-We will.
-But what?
School's closed!
One nail draws out another.
Sh!
-Anybody else with you?
-No, we're alone.
Come on.
-…decide our history!
-Yeah! That's right!
Because the flame
of the revolution burns
inside each one of you!
-Yeah!
-And we're not alone in this!
We are the majority!
And we are tired of living under
the oppression of the Conservatives!
Out with the Conservatives!
And this town was founded on
the very principles of liberty
and equality for all!
Out with Conservatives!
That is why we all need
to get out and vote!
-Yeah, that's right!
-And we'll go out and vote with cojones!
We will vote with dignity and courage!
-Long live Macondo!
-That's it now!
We'll go out there and vote
because Macondo has always been Liberal!
Macondo's Liberal!
Macondo's Liberal! Macondo's Liberal!
Macondo's Liberal! Macondo's Lib…
Elections are now officially open
for the first time ever
in the history of Macondo.
As instructed
by Doctor Noguera,
the men submitting red ballots
had to drink from their small bottle
as proof of their commitment
to the Liberal Party.
Please, next in line.
Two hundred and thirty-six votes total.
One hundred and thirty-two
red ballots for the Liberal Party
and 104 blue ballots
for the Conservative Party.
We'll switch 'em then.
A hundred and thirty-two blue votes,
104 red votes.
Once you've finished, Sergeant,
then seal the urn.
Tomorrow we'll send them off
to the capital to be counted.
If I were a Liberal,
that'd be a reason for me to go to war.
My boy, lucky for you,
if you were a Liberal, son-in-law or not,
you would've never seen this.
Mm.
That night, Rebeca managed
to thank God for having been born
before she lost herself
in the inconceivable pleasure
of that unbearable pain.
Tell your father-in-law
to return the knives.
Ours and the whole town's.
We have nothing to cook with. Hmm.
Something wrong?
I'm getting married to Rebeca.
Don't be ridiculous.
You two are siblings.
We'll get married in three days.
We're not asking for permission.
This is an atrocity.
If you go through with it,
you won't set foot in this house again!
Perfect.
You are all cordially invited.
Úrsula never forgave
what she considered to be
an inconceivable act of disrespect.
And Amaranta was never able to
get over her resentment towards Rebeca.
Let's begin with baton 14.
Fourteen, please.
Look at the pentagram.
Very good.
On my count.
One, two, three, four.
Very good.
One, two, three, four-- Excuse me.
-We're in class.
-I'm marrying Rebeca.
You're her brother.
That's not important.
You can't do that.
That's unnatural.
And besides, the law forbids it.
Fuck what you think is natural.
I don't care what you think. Listen.
I'm telling you myself, Pietro,
so you don't bother going to Rebeca.
Are we clear?
Mr. Moscote.
Oh, hello, son.
-It's too early for dominoes.
-I know that.
So then, what's the matter?
The knives, sir.
Now all of the women in Macondo,
including my mother,
are angry that they have
nothing to cook with.
The knives have been sent
to the provincial capital
with the rest of the confiscated weapons,
as proof beyond dispute that the Liberals
are all preparing for war.
General Medina sends
an urgent message from Manaure!
-What's happened? How are things?
-The Conservatives stole the elections.
There's been fraud nationwide.
There's certain areas
where Liberals are taking up arms.
We should be doing the same!
Well, to do the same,
we'd need weapons ourselves, Arcadio!
Be careful.
In Riohacha,
they executed all of the Liberals
that decided to confront the government.
Yah!
Today, we have come together
to celebrate the marriage
between José Arcadio Buendía
and Rebeca Buendía,
who, contrary to the gossip and rumors
being spread around town,
are not siblings!
In the name of the Father,
the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
Amen.
Hey!
Arcadio never knew
that José Arcadio was his father.
Now, you're my wife!
Yeah!
Mm.
Rebeca and José Arcadio rented
a little house in front of the cemetery.
That's our house.
Don't look over there! Don't look!
Don't look!
And they settled in
with no furniture but the hammock.
That night,
a scorpion bit Rebeca on the foot.
But that did not keep them
from a scandalous honeymoon.
The town residents prayed
that such unrestrained passion
would not disturb the peace of the dead.
-Do you have any knives, Catarino?
-Not even one to cut a lime.
Of course not.
Hey, Catarino.
Give me a drink, please, will you?
You guys can keep talking.
Pretend I'm not here.
Tell me, Aureliano,
what do you believe your father would say
if he knew that you had become
a Conservative in the end?
I don't identify
as Conservative or Liberal.
But if push came to shove,
then I'd choose Liberal.
Conservatives are complete frauds.
That's what they are.
Are you sure that's
really what you think about them?
I've never been more sure.
Catarino!
We are
currently planning a revolution.
What sort of revolution?
Well, they're coordinating
a series of attacks, nationwide actually,
with the intention of killing
every official for the Conservatives
and their respective families.
That's why we need you on our side.
We need your help
to kill Apolinar Moscote,
his wife, and six daughters.
Conservatism must be
cut off at the source.
You know what, Noguera?
You're neither a revolutionary
nor a Liberal.
Not at all.
You are nothing but a butcher!
That's exactly what you are.
You wanna know what you are,
Aureliano Buendía?
You're a guy that's too sentimental.
A man with no vision.
Give me back the bottle.
I'd be more than glad to.
You coward.
You're just a fucking coward.
And cowards never make history.
Gentlemen.
Pietro Crespi continued
having lunch at the house on Tuesdays,
rising above the failure of his marriage
to Rebeca with a serene kind of dignity.
Amaranta looked after him
with loving diligence.
For Pietro Crespi,
the woman whom he always considered
and treated as a child
was a revelation.
So what, then? Do you plan to kill me
like you plan on killing the Moscotes?
-What?
-Hey.
What are you even talking about right now?
Hey! Calm down!
Those men outside that were following me.
That's what I'm talking about.
We sent men to follow you,
but not to murder you, all right?
We knew it was a matter of time
before you gave our plan away.
Let him go.
Listen to me.
If I wanted to rat on you,
I would've done it ages ago.
But I'm not a traitor.
However,
the day you plan to kill my father-in-law…
is the same day that I will be standing
by his door defending him.
-Go on!
-Hey!
This building…
No!
…is now property of the National Army!
-No, no! I teach at this school!
-Let's go!
-Let her go!
-Get out!
-Let go of her!
-Go clear the back rooms.
Okay! Okay, okay, okay! Okay!
-Keep moving! Keep moving!
-Don't… don't touch her!
-Get out!
-Don't! Don't… don't shoot! Please!
Here. Come here.
Just get behind me. There.
Building secured! Let's go!
We should get out of here. Okay?
No, please! Let go of me!
-Help!
-Shut up!
Ah! You people have no right to do this!
Criminals have no rights. Silence!
-For God's sake, have mercy on this man!
-Let go of me!
No, no, no!
-Please! This is a violation! Help me!
-Hey!
-You have no right!
-You are violating my rights!
-You have no right to do this!
-Arcadio!
Let me go!
Don't try to be a hero.
You know those men can kill you.
Those men are gonna
kill us all if we don't do something.
You can't do this…
Your choice, Aureliano!
What side are you on?
…without giving me a fair trial!
Thank you.
You can't just execute
Alirio Noguera like that!
Give your soldiers the order
to stop the execution.
I'm afraid there's nothing I can do.
It's up to Captain Gómez now.
What exactly are you saying?
Once they declare a state of emergency,
the military's put in charge.
Ready!
Aim!
Long live the revolution!
Fire!
-Nothing, just--
-I asked you a question!
-Please!
-Tell me or hand it over!
-Hand it over!
-Let go of me!
I'll shut you up!
Wait! Ah! Help!
Help! Please!
Just let him go!
No!
Please help me!
No! No! No!
No!
Captain, that dog had rabies.
Sir, please, I need a doctor.
Please, sir!
Aureliano, don't be stupid.
You'll get yourself killed out there.
You're not made for this.
Aureliano, son, listen to me.
I'm the one in charge.
Take care, my son.
Aureliano, please.
Take care of him as if he were your own.
And take care of yourself as well.
You hear me?
Aureliano, please don't leave me.
Please, listen to me.
My son, please…
No, don't leave us.
Don't go, please.
What's the matter, Aureliano?
Let's round up the men.
We have to go to war.
We've got no weapons!
Then we'll use theirs.
Who is it?
Aureliano.
Aureliano?
What's wrong?
We're kicking the Conservatives
out of Macondo.
There's me,
Gerineldo, Magnífico, and a few more.
And?
Come fight with us.
We're joining
General Medina's revolutionary army.
I've already gone and seen
everything I needed to see out there.
My place is here now… with her.
Good luck.
Aureliano!
Of course I remember.
That night…
I said,
"It's like the whole world is shaking."
Why do you think we as men all fear death?
Take care and come back alive.
Aureliano.
Mm!
Let's do it.
Get him out!
Ah! I can't just be executed
without being given a fair trial!
Oh!
Honor the motherland!
Fire now!
So, Aureliano…
What? What is it?
Are we joining General Medina?
You're not.
I need you to stay here instead and assume
the post of civil and military chief.
You keep our home safe.
Make sure we find this town
better than how we left it.
Yes. Yes.
Now hurry and make sure
everyone's well armed.
Yes.
Please! Don't kill me!
Don't kill me! Don't kill me!
-I'm begging you. Don't kill me! Please!
-Sh, sh, sh, sh, sh.
Enough, Moscote.
We freed Macondo
from the Conservatives.
But I assure you,
you and your family are safe.
You have my word.
What is this madness, son?
Have you gone insane?
This isn't madness!
This is war.
And don't you ever call me "son" again.
Am I clear?
As of this very moment,
I am now Colonel Aureliano Buendía.
BASED ON THE NOVEL BY
GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ